Guide to the Donald Lyons Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Donald Lyons papers
1910-2010
GEN MSS 1360
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
20.25
(24 boxes) + 1 broadside and 1 computer
The Donald Lyons papers consist of writings by Lyons, including film and theater criticism; personal and business correspondence, including letters from Danny Fields and Roger Darrobers; notebooks; personal papers and artwork; academic papers; photographs of friends, including Edie Sedgwick; videocassettes of "Theater Talk" and "Inside Broadway" programs; and computer files.
Lyons, Donald
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 24 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 25, 26 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Donald Lyons (1938-2011)
Donald Lyons (1938-2011) was an American film and drama critic for publications including the New Criterion, Film Comment, the Wall Street Journal, and the New York Post. He also contributed to the magazines Rock Scene, Hit Parader, Rock & Soul, and Country Rhythms. Lyons received a bachelor's degree from Fordham University (1959) and a master's degree from Harvard University, then taught English literature and classics at Harvard, Rutgers University, and New York University. He was the author of the influential volume Independent Visions: A Critical Introduction to Recent Independent American Film (New York: Ballantine Books, 1994).
Lyons was also well known for his association with Andy Warhol's Factory, where he acted in several films, contributed to Andy Warhol's Interview magazine, and helped shape the artistic vision of that group of artists and writers. Among his close friends were Edie Sedgwick and Danny Fields.
Scope and Contents
The Donald Lyons papers consist of writings by Lyons, including film and theater criticism; personal and business correspondence, including letters from Danny Fields and Roger Darrobers; notebooks; personal papers and artwork; academic papers; photographs of friends, including Edie Sedgwick; videocassettes of appearances by Lyons on the television programs "Theater Talk" and "Inside Broadway;" and computer files.
Arrangement
Organized into nine series: I. Writings and Criticism, 1957-2004. II. Correspondence, 1920s-2000s. III. Notebooks, 1950s-2000s. IV. Academic Papers, 1950s-2000s. V. Family and Personal Papers, 1910s-2010. VI. Photographs and Ephemera, 1920s-2000s. VII. Printed Materials, 1930s-1990s. VIII. Audiovisual Materials, 1994-2001. IX. Electronic Media, circa 1990s.
Film criticism -- United States; Film critics -- United States -- Archives; Dramatic criticism -- United States; Theater critics -- United States -- Archives; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Born digital -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Film critics -- United States -- 20th Century; Theater critics -- United States -- 20th Century; Darrobers, Roger; Fields, Danny, 1939-; Lyons, Donald; Sedgwick, Edie; Warhol, Andy, 1928-1987; Andy Warhol's Factory (New York, N.Y.)
- Writings and Criticism, 1957-2004; Series I; 4.37; (5 boxes)
  - Independent Visions, 1993-1994; 21 folders (Box 1)
  - Independent Visions, 1992-1994; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - "Oscar" material, 1969-1994 (Box 3)
  - Unpublished theater criticism, circa 1991; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Wall Street Journal published and manuscript theater criticism, circa 1990 (Box 3)
  - Published and unpublished movie and theater material, MD magazine, circa 1991; 2.0 (Box 3)
  - Published and unpublished criticism ( Details magazine), circa 1990; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Unpublished movie criticism, circa 1993; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Published Details movie criticism and unpublished movie writings, circa 1990; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Published Details movie criticism, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Draft, probably for Independent Visions, circa 1993 (Box 3)
  - Visconti writing (published), clippings on censorship ("porn rock"), notes, Bruce Springsteen article ( Rock Video magazine), circa 1985 (Box 3)
  - Galleys, New Criterion, theater, 1990-1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Writing for Film Comment and Crawdaddy, published interview with Cukor/Lambert, published book reviews, poem by Janice Thaddeus, circa 1991 (Box 3)
  - Wall Street Journal published book reviews, unpublished movie criticism, Film Comment correspondence and manuscript, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Published film and theater reviews in Crawdaddy, Interview, and the New York Post, 1971-1973, 1997-1999; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Clippings of reviews in the Wall Street Journal, 1983-1999 (Box 4)
  - Writings by others, clippings, and D.C. movie lists, 1976-2000 (Box 4)
  - Clippings by others and film writing from New Criterion and Rock Scene, circa 1966, 1992-1995 (Box 4)
  - Theater, film, classics writings for the Wall Street Journal, circa 1995 (Box 4)
  - Published and manuscript film writings and notes, Rock Scene article, circa 1970-2000 (Box 4)
  - Death in Venice (movie) reviews, 1971, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Film clippings by others, clippings from Details, circa 1988-1992 (Box 4)
  - Reviews and writings, mostly manuscripts, some published, and list of best films, circa 1988-2000 (Box 4)
  - Film biographies by Lyons, materials about Anthony Rapp from Dazed and Confused, and miscellaneous film writing by Lyons, circa 1996 (Box 4)
  - Writings, clippings by others, circa 1970-2004 (Box 4)
  - Published writings, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Modernism, circa 1987-1994 (Box 4)
  - Movie, theater, and dance materials and clippings, circa 1971-2003 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 2000 (Box 4)
  - Published and manuscript reviews, mainly from New Criterion, and a possible draft for Independent Visions, circa 1990-1997 (Box 4)
  - Writings for Film Comment, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Published and manuscript writings for New Criterion and Wall Street Journal, circa 1975-1996; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous writings, circa 1995-2002 (Box 5)
  - Writings for New Criterion, 1991-1997; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Nemo's Almanac, 1971-1982 (Box 5)
  - Published writings, clippings, complete issues of Film Comment, Almodóvar interview from Interview, circa 1989-1993 (Box 5)
  - Film research clippings, circa 1991-1997 (Box 5)
  - Film and review notes, Interview magazine, 1970s (Box 5)
  - Classic Films, circa 1957-1964 (Box 5)
  - Materials for film biographies, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Writings by Tom Beller, circa 1991 (Box 5)
  - Lists of films, circa 1987-1997 (Box 5)
  - Donald Lyons and friends, circa 1971-1999 (Box 5)
  - River Phoenix, 1991-1994 (Box 5)
  - Lyons' translation of Antigone, circa 1959-1995 (Box 5)
  - Writings, stamps, and other papers, circa 1987-1995 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, 1920s-2000s; Series II; 2.08; (2 boxes)
  - General correspondence, 1960s-2000s; 24 folders (Box 6)
  - General correpondence, 1960s-2000s; 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Danny Fields, 1960s-1990s (Box 7)
  - Ed Hennessey ("Eudora" or "Edita"), 1965-1995 (Box 7)
  - Ed Hood, 1960s-1970s (Box 7)
  - Harold Peterson ("Halloween"), 1960s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Eric Bentley, 1990s-2000s (Box 7)
  - Roger Darrobers, regarding French cinema, 1970s-1980s; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Family and friends, 1920s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Publishing correspondence, 1970s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 7)
- Notebooks, 1950s-2000s; Series III; 1.04; (1 box)
  - Notebooks, diaries, and planners, 1950s-2000s; 17 folders (Box 8)
- Academic Papers, 1950s-2000s; Series IV; 1.67; (3 boxes)
  - Fordham University paper, "Homer: a redefinition in the light of modern inquiry", 1959 (Box 9)
  - School writings and other academic papers, circa 1950s-1990s; 7 folders (Box 9)
  - University writings, circa 1959; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Other academic papers, including student writing and class materials, 1960s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Rutgers University exam booklets filled with Lyons' writings on film, philosophy, and literature, circa 1980s-2000s; 8 folders (Box 11)
  - Photocopied classics writings in English and German, undated (Box 11)
  - Student tests and other academic papers, 1960s-1980s (Box 11)
- Family and Personal Papers, 1910s-2010; Series V; 6.13; (5 boxes)
  - Writings and drawings sent to Lyons, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 12)
  - Drawing, undated (Box 12)
  - Copy of Tennessee Williams' Slapstick Tragedy and a New York Times clipping, 1965, 1990 (Box 12)
  - High school yearbook, 1955 (Box 12)
  - Personal and travel documents, 1940s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Travel papers, circa 1970s-2010; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Family insurance policies, birth certificates, house deed, 1928-1994 (Box 12)
  - Portrait of child and older portrait of children, circa 1910s, circa 1930s (Box 12)
  - Family papers, photographs, and slides, circa 1944-1986 (Box 12)
  - Dames poster, Margo Channing poster, sheet music, 1934, 1995 (Box 12)
  - School objects, 1951-1989 (Box 12)
  - WordPerfect training manual, circa 1991-1993 (Box 12)
  - Printed materials including news and magazine clippings, e-mails and writings by others, circa 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Script by Billy Squier, 1995 (Box 12)
  - Clifford Odets material, In Hell + Why, 1996 (Box 12)
  - Childhood papers and books, circa 1944-1994; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Poetry booklets and magazines, 1965-1972 (Box 13)
  - Some Songs of the Sidewinders and related corresondence, circa 1971-1999 (Box 13)
  - Baby shoes and viewfinder (Box 14)
  - Drawing (Box 15)
  - Clippings, 1970s-1990s (Box 15)
  - Poster (Box 15)
  - Legal documents re: Ed Hood's estate, 1980s (Box 15)
  - Pen and ink drawings, circa 1983 (Box 16 (Broadside))
- Photographs and Ephemera, 1920s-2000s; Series VI; 2.54; (4 boxes)
  - Family photograph album, circa 1920s-1970 (Box 17)
  - Family photograph albums, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 18)
  - Family scrapbook, 1940s-1970s (Box 19)
  - Childhood photographs, clippings, postcards, and other family material, circa 1920s-1980s (Box 20)
  - Photographs of Donald Lyons, circa 1950s-2000s (Box 20)
  - Photographs of friends and family, 1970s-1990s (Box 20)
  - Celebrity and other photographs, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 20)
  - Edie Sedgwick photographs and other materials, 1960s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 20)
- Printed Materials, 1930s-1990s; Series VII; 1.79; (3 boxes)
  - Magazines with River Phoenix articles, circa 1990-1992 (Box 21)
  - Magazines with articles written by Lyons, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 22)
  - Issues of Magnetoscope, 1972 (Box 23)
  - Printed research materials, circa 1930s-1990s; 11 folders (Box 23)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1994-2001; Series VIII; 0.42; 1 box; 7
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "Inside Broadway": Bruce Jay Friedman and Donald Lyons, part 2, 1994 January 19; 1 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002099362304)
  - "Inside Broadway": Donald Lyons, 1995 January 12; 1 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002099362296)
  - "Inside Broadway": Howard Kissel and Donald Lyons, 1996 June 3; 1 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002099362320)
    Scope and Contents
    A note included with this videocassette, dated 9/9/96, reads: Dear Donald: I love this show. You and Howard Kissel were both great. Thank you for doing it. I'm sorry it took so long to get this tape to you. It looks like we'll be back on the air in November, and I devoutly hope you'll be our guest again this season. All the best, Susan Haskins.
  - "Theater Talk": Jacques le Sourd and Donald Lyons, 1997 December 17; 1 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002099362312)
    A note included with this videocassette reads: Thank you again. This was a very popular show. [Wz] look forward to your next appearance. All the best, Susan.
  - "Theater Talk": Jacques le Sourd and Donald Lyons, 1998 May 14; 1 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002099362346)
  - "Theater Talk": le Sourd, Lyons, Morehouse, Simonson, 1998 October 30; 1 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002099362338)
  - "Theatre Talk" # 716: Edward Albee, 2001 February 2; 1 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002099362353)
- Electronic Media, circa 1990s; Series IX; 0.21; (1 box) + 1 computer
  Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Writing by Tom Beller," one 3.5" floppy disk, circa 1991 (Box 25)
  - Nautilus PC tower, 1990s (Box 26)